Guide to the Anthony Dey Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Anthony Dey Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company records
1821-1855
1830-1835
WA MSS S-1743
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.87
(6 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, documents, account books, case files, financial papers, and printed material which document one of the earliest Texas land companies. The correspondence concerns the company's business, dealing with agents, and receiving reports from Texas, Mexico City, and various places in Europe. Principal correspondents include John T. Mason, William H. Sumner, Jonathan Turnbull, G. H. Paulsen, and William S. Allen. Other papers in the collection include copies of grants, agreeements with agents, papers relating to court cases, highly detailed account books, printed scrip, and a small amount of printed material including newspapers, broadsides, and pamphlets.
Dey, Anthony, 1776-1859
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased from High Ridge Books, Inc. in 1992-1993 on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
GALVESTON BAY AND TEXAS LAND COMPANY
The Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company was organized in New York on October 16, 1830 by Anthony Dey, George Curtis, and William H. Sumner. The company was to work as agents of empresarios Joseph Vehlein, David G. Burnet, and Lorenzo de Zavala, who had grants of land east of the San Jacinto River and south of Nacogdoches. Anthony Dey (1776-1859), a lawyer in New York, was the president of the company; the other trustees were George Curtis (1799-1884), also a lawyer in New York, and William H. Sumner (1780-1861), a lawyer in Boston.
The company was the first commercial effort in the United States to emulate Stephen Austin's plans to colonize Texas, and it published some of the earliest accounts of Texas printed in English. The company owned none of the land to be colonized but instead sold scrip which was a permit to settle. The company's American agents included Jose Antonio Mexia and John T. Mason; it also had several agents in Europe soliciting recruits. Once in Texas, the settlers would have to complete the requirements of the Mexican colonization law before they could obtain title to their land. Restrictions imposed by the government of Mexico frustrated the company's efforts, and it became a strong supporter of Texas independence.
In November 1835 the General Council of the provisional government of Texas closed the land office. At that time the company had not received the premium lands (three haciendas and two labors) the Mexican government had promised to empresarios for settling 200 families. When the Republic passed a law in June 1837 that permitted empresarios to institute suit to establish their claims so long as neither aliens nor assignees of aliens should benefit by the law, the company authorized Robert Rose, successor of John T. Mason, to enter a suit. In 1848 the courts ruled that the term aliens applied to assignees of the company and that Rose was not qualified to sue. With the failure of the suit, the company went out of business. Even after this time, however, Anthony Dey continued to pursue his claims against the Mexican government in court, and was sued by other members of the company.
Scope and Contents
The Anthony Dey Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company Records consist of correspondence, documents, account books, case files, financial papers, and printed material which document the workings of one of the earliest Texas land companies. The collection spans the years 1828-1855, but the bulk of the material dates from the most active years of the company, 1830-1835.
The Records are organized into five series: Correspondence, Agreements, Grants and Proposals, Court Actions, Financial Papers, and Printed Material. Boxes 4-6 contain Oversize material.
Series I, Correspondence (1828-1855), contains letters addressed to either Anthony Dey or the Galveston Bay Company and letters from Dey, as well as a small group of third party correspondence. The series is arranged chronologically. The earliest correspondences date from the time that Lorenzo de Zavala obtained his grant; later letters concern the company's business, including correspondence with agents both in Texas and Europe, sending instructions and receiving news from Texas, Mexico City and various places in Europe. There are also inquiries in response to the Company's advertisements, letters from surveyors, and discussions of the advantages of to the United States if it were to purchase Texas from Mexico. Principal correspondents include John T. Mason, William H. Sumner, Jonathan Turnbull, G. H. Paulsen, and William S. Allen. There is a gap in the correspondence from January 1836 to June 1849. The letters from 1849-1851 are written by William H. Sumner to Anthony Dey and concern a memorial to President James K. Polk that Sumner was preparing. Five folders of correspondence fragments have been placed at the end of the series. One of these, folder number 18, contains correspondence, probably written to John T. Mason, discussing the merits of the United States owning Texas.
Series II, Agreements, Grants, and Proposals (1826-1835) contains documents related to the people and events discussed in the correspondence of Series I. The files include copies of the grants of the empresarios, agreements with agents, letters of attorney for agents to sell scrip, and proposals of surveyors. Series III, Court Actions (1832-1852), contains papers relating to four court cases in which the company or Dey was involved, which are arranged by case. The first, Anthony Dey, impleaded with George Curtis ads. Charles A. Carter concerns a dispute with a land agent over payment for services rendered. The second case, Anthony Dey ads. Peter Reinoudt and Stewart Newell concerns Anthony Dey's dispute with his agents Newell and Reinoudt over the allocation of the grant lands. The case of Galveston Bay Company vs. Federal Government of Mexico consists of Anthony Dey's claims against the government of Mexico for the expenses incurred and premiums not gained due to governmental interference. The case of Stephen Whitney et al. vs. Anthony Dey et al. concerns a complaint brought by Stephen Whitney and others who had been appointed directors of the Galveston Bay Company.
Anthony Dey's personal financial papers are included with Galveston Bay Company papers in Series IV, Financial Papers (1821-1837). A two volume, highly detailed, account book dating from 1821 to 1834 carries both personal and business accounts, from the payment of servants, and purchase of horses and bread to the sale of shares in the Galveston Bay Company. Also present is Anthony Dey's bankbook as trustee of the company, and eight printed scrip, one of which was printed in Germany. Series V, Printed Material, includes newspapers, pamphlets (one published in Germany), broadsides, and other printed ephemera. Several items in this series have been cataloged separately, but remain with the collection.
Oversize contains material from Series II, IV, and V, arranged in box order.
Land companies -- Texas; Land grants -- Texas; Real property -- Texas; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- Colonization; Texas -- Description and travel; Texas -- Emigration and immigration; Texas -- History -- To 1846; Account books; Case files; Land grants; Allen, William S.; Burnet, David G. (David Gouverneur), 1788-1870; Curtis, George, 1799-1884; Dey, Anthony, 1776-1859; Mason, John T. (John Thomson), 1787-1850; Paulsen, G. H.; Sumner, William H. (William Hyslop), 1780-1861; Turnbull, Jonathan; Vehlein, Joseph; Zavala, Lorenzo de, 1788-1836; Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company
- Correspondence, 1828-1855; Series I; 1.67; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains letters addressed to either Anthony Dey or the Galveston Bay Company, letters from Dey, as well as a few third party letters. Correspondence fragments are filed at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1828 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1829 Apr (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1836 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1850 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1851 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1855 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence fragments, 1831, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Correspondence fragment, [1834] (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Agreements, Grants and Proposals, 1826-1835; Series II; 0.2
  Series II, Agreements, Grants and Proposals, is arranged chronologically.
  - Copy of David G. Burnet's grant, 1826 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Translation of the grant to Lorenzo de Zavala, 1829 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Revoking agreement with Joseph R. Brazier, 1830 Dec 25 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Draft proposition of Barnabus Bartol, 1831 Jan (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Draft proposition of Daniel McLaren & Co., 1831 Jan (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Agreement with Benjamin Poor, 1831 Oct 11
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 79
  - Agreement with Jane M. McManus, 1832 Sep 12
    Three copies, two of them signed by McManus and Dey
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 80.
  - Anthony Dey's letter of attorney to Jane M. McManus authorizing her to sell scrip for labors of land, 1832 Sep 12 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    See also: Oversize, box 4, folder 81
  - Contract with David Ayres, 1832 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Agreement with Barrett Ames, 1832 Oct 16 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Answer to proposal of Jane M. McManus, 1832 Oct 26
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 82
  - Trustees letter of attorney to John T. Mason, 1832 Nov 9 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    One letter of attorney written on the verso of a printed broadsheet dated December 10, 1830
    See also: Oversize, box 4, folder 83.
  - Agreement with John Turnbull, 1834 Jul 5
    Two copies, both signed by Turnbull and Dey
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 84.
  - Agreement with George Henry Paulsen, 1834 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Agreement with Moses Willard Wetmore, 1834 Dec 1 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Agreement with Rollin C. Hall, 1834 Dec 24 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Schedule of Contracts made by A. Dey for the sale of Texas Scrip, 1834-35 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Agreement with William S. Allen, 1835 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Alphabetical list of names and addresses
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 85
  - Copy of Lorenzo de Zavala's grant, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Form for the grants for land in Texas
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 86
  - Proposal of surveyors Charles Zimpel & J. J. S. Hassler, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Translation into Spanish, Trustees letter of attorney to Jose Antonio Mexia, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Court Actions, 1832-1852; Series III; 0.4
  Series III, Court Actions, is arranged chronologically by case.
  - DEY ADS. CARTER
    Full case name: Anthony Dey, impleaded with George Curtis ads. Charles A. Carter
    - Copy of accounts current and notice received by C. A. Carter (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Tender of delivery, 1832 Mar 17 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - ANTHONY DEY ADS. PETER REINOUDT AND STEWART NEWELL
    - Interrogatories to be administered to William S. Allen and his deposition, 1836 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - GALVESTON BAY COMPANY VS. FEDERAL GOVERNMENT OF MEXICO
    - Abstract of exhibits and affidavits (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Anthony Dey's claim for damages from the Mexican Government, 1849, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Deposition of Charles A. Carter, 1849 Jun (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Draft of Anthony Dey's affidavit, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Draft stated account of Trustees, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Draft of statement by Trustees, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Inventory of exhibits, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - List of papers sent to James J. Roosevelt, Member of Congress, 1849 Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Memorial to James K. Polk, 1846 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Reference to exhibits, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - STEPHEN WHITNEY ET AL. VS. ANTHONY DEY ET AL.
    - Answers of Anthony Dey and George Curtis (Box 2, Folder 54-56)
    - Depositions on the part of the plaintiffs, 1852 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Interrogatories to be administered to Benjamin W. Bonney, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Interrogatories to be administered to Alfred Roe, Andrew S. Garr, and John Whitehead (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Points for the defendants Dey and Curtis (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
- Financial Papers, 1821-1837; Series IV; 2.2
  Series IV, Financial Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Account book belonging to Anthony Dey, 1821-28
    See: Oversize, box 5, folder 92
  - Account book belonging to Anthony Dey, 1828-34
    See: Oversize, box 6, folder 93
  - Miscellaneous receipts, 1823-32 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    See also: Oversize, box 4, folder 87
  - Assignment of scrip. Joseph R. Brazier to Azel Snow, 1830 Dec 22 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Bill of William P. Harris, 1831 Sep 8 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Statement of accounts with agents, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Scrip (5) for one labor made out to Charles A. Carter, [1832 Mar 17] (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Bank book. Anthony Dey with City Bank as Trustee of the G.B. & T.L.C., 1832-36 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Stock transfers, 1832-33, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Bill of lading for papers belonging to Anthony Dey being shipped to Le Havre, 1834 Oct 23 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Declaration of deposit of 12 sitios with Samuel Ward to secure $2000 for the Steamboat Connecticut, 1834 Nov 19 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Claim for commission to purchase fee simple, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Certificate for four shares made out to Joseph Osborne, Jr., 1837 Jan 20 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Scrip (1) for one labor made out to Richard V. Dey, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Scrip (1) for one labor made out to Rodman Moulton, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Scrip (1), in German, for one labor, not completed
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 88
  - Statement of Anthony Dey's accounts against the Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company (Box 3, Folder 75)
- Printed Material, 1830-1850; Series V; 0.2
  Series V, Printed Material, is arranged chronologically.
  - To all to whom these Presents shall come or may concern. We, Lorenzo de Zavala,...Joseph Vehlein...David G. Burnet..Do...appoint...Anthony Dey, William H. Sumner, and George Curtis ...the true and lawful attorneys... of us...., 1830 Dec 10
    Broadsheet, with letter of attorney written on the verso.
    See: Box 4, folder 83
  - Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company Scrip, completed in manuscript, [1832], n.d.
    See: Box 3, folders 66, 73, 74, and box 4, folder 88
  - El Fenix de la Liberdad Tom. IV, Num. 40. Mexico, 1834 Feb 9
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 89
  - Clipping advertising the Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company, [1834] (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company. Notice. A meeting of the Stockholders of the Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company was held at the Shakespear Hotel...., 1835 Jan 20 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    Handbill. Large tears along old folds, affecting text. Signed in manuscript "W. M. Willson, Secy."
  - Texas and Emigrant's Guide Vol. 1, No. 5. Nacogdoches, Texas, 1835 Dec 26
    See: Broadside case, folder 94
  - Texas und Einladung zu einer vortheilhaften Unsiedelung daselbst.... Stuttgart, 1835
    Pamphlet
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 90.
  - Galveston Bay and Texas Land Company Share certificate, completed in manuscript, 1837 Jan 20
    See: Box 3, folder 72
  - Claim of the Union Land Company, n.p., [1850] (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Portrait of Anthony Dey, n.d.
    See: Oversize, box 4, folder 91
- Oversize, 1.67
  Oversize contains material from Series II, IV, and V, arranged in box order.
  - Agreement with Benjamin Poor (in Series II) (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Agreement with Jane M. McManus (in Series II), 1832 Sep 12 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Anthony Dey's letter of attorney to Jane M. McManus authorizing her to sell scrip for labors of land (in Series II), 1832 Sep 12 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Answer to proposal of Jane M. McManus (in Series II), 1832 Oct 26 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Trustees letter of attorney to John T. Mason (in Series II), 1832 Nov 9 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Agreement with John Turnbull (in Series II), 1834 Jul 5 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Alphabetical list of names and addresses (in Series II) (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Form for the grants for land in Texas (in Series II) (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Miscellaneous receipts (in Series IV), 1823-32 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Scrip (1), in German, for one labor, not completed (in Series IV) (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - El Fenix de la Liberdad Tom. IV, Num. 40. Mexico (in Series V), 1834 Feb 9 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Texas und Einladung zu einer vortheilhaften Unsiedelung daselbst.... Stuttgart (in Series V), 1835 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Portrait of Anthony Dey (in Series V), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Account book belonging to Anthony Dey (in Series IV), 1821-28 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Account book belonging to Anthony Dey (in Series IV), 1828-34 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Texas and Emigrant's Guide Vol. 1, No. 5. Nacogdoches, Texas (in Series V), 1835 Dec 26 (Box bsd, folder 94)